<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England and East-India inconsistent in their manufactures being an answer to a treatise intituled, An essay on the East-India trade by the author of, The essay of wayes and means.</title>
            <author>Pollexfen, John, b. ca. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12758182</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12758182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93459</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England and East-India inconsistent in their manufactures being an answer to a treatise intituled, An essay on the East-India trade by the author of, The essay of wayes and means.</title>
                  <author>Pollexfen, John, b. ca. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to John Pollexfen.  Cf. also DNB.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Davenant, Charles, 1656-1714. --  Essay on the East India trade.</term>
               <term>East India Company.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  India.</term>
               <term>India --  Commerce --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLAND AND EAST-INDIA Inconſiſtent in Their <hi>Manufactures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING AN ANSWER TO A TREATISE, INTITULED, <hi>An Eſſay on the</hi> Eaſt-India <hi>Trade.</hi> By the Author of, <hi>The Eſſay of Wayes and Means.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93459:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Some Conſiderations upon Reading a Treatiſe, Intituled, <hi>An Eſſay on the</hi> East-India <hi>Trade.</hi> By the Author of the Eſſay on <hi>Wayes</hi> and <hi>Means.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE many Objections formerly made againſt the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe was carried on by the Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Coyn or Bullion, and by the Importation of Manufactured Goods and Toyes, were uſually anſwered by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates for that Trade, that ſuch Goods could not be injurious, becauſe were not ſpent in <hi>England,</hi> but Tranſported to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Markets, and thereby occaſioned the Importation of more Bullion than ever was Exported: But the Truth (which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly denyed) being now owned by this Treatiſe, that one half of the ſaid Goods are conſumed at Home, and that thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactured Goods do hinder the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what are Fabrickt by our own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93459:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Landed Men have now Reaſon to conclude, that they are more concern'd in this Conteſt, than the <hi>Weavers,</hi> as well for their particular Intereſt as the publick good: And therefore the Conſiderations here Offered are thought neceſſary, that theſe new Maxims and Arguments may be Examined; becauſe the Rents of Land as well as Preſervation of our Coyn, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our Manufactures, and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of our People, doth much depend upon what Reſolutions may be taken for the ſettling of this Trade.</p>
            <p>The General Notions about Trade from Page the Firſt to Page the Eleventh are poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned, to be conſidered at the end of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Page the Twelfth aſſerts,
<q>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> That the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade is beneficial to <hi>England.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> That to Prohibit the Wearing of <hi>India</hi> Wrought Silks, Bengals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will be deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Trade of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To juſtifie the firſt Propoſition, it is ſaid, That we Export but 400000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum,</hi> of which ⅛ to ¼ is in our Home made Goods, and that the produce of 200000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> brought home and ſpent in <hi>England,</hi> being the one half, yields us 800000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93459:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the produce of the other 200000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> being in Goods ſent Abroad to Foreign Markets, yields us another ſum of 800000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.:</hi>
               </abbr> And therefore that <hi>England</hi> gains by this Trade 1200000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> clear. <hi>Page</hi> 16, 53.</p>
            <p>Inſtead of offering Vouchers to prove this Accompt, it is ſaid, That it muſt be clear Gains, becauſe the half ſpent in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> prevents the Exportation of treble that ſum in Money, which would otherwayes be carried out for the purchaſing of Silks and Linnens in Foreign Parts, and that the other half muſt be clear Gains, becauſe no one verſed in Merchandize will deny it. <hi>Page</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>And for a further confirmation, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor tells us <hi>Page</hi> 17, That he hath cogent Reaſons to believe this Nation did increaſe in Riches from <hi>Anno</hi> 1656 to <hi>Anno</hi> 1688, 2 Millions <hi>per Annum;</hi> and that after much ſtudy and thought did find, that the ſaid increaſe did ariſe 900000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> by our Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Trades, 500000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> by our Products and Manufactures, and 600000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> from the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade; which we muſt believe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaith the matter is not capable of any clear demonſtration to the contrary. <hi>Page</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>It is thought convenient to anſwer this Accompt with an Accompt much different, and yet probably as true, <hi>viz.</hi> That there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93459:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath been Exported for <hi>India</hi> Annually ever ſince <hi>Anno</hi> 1673. when the Trade in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factured Goods from thence begun firſt to increaſe till <hi>Anno</hi> 1690, about 600000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> in Bullion by the Company, Private Traders or Interlopers, from <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> and that the Goods brought from thence never brought back into <hi>England,</hi> nor ſaved the going out of 200000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> in Bullion: And therefore that this Trade, inſtead of being profitable to us, hath exhauſted about 400000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> of our Treaſure, and done us much Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief by the Importation of ſuch Goods; and that our Riches have not Increaſed ever ſince <hi>Anno</hi> 1666, but have Annually De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed very much by Trade.</p>
            <p>But before any Argument ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd upon, which of theſe Accompts is moſt Juſtifiable, 'tis requiſite to agree upon matter of Fact and Principles, particularly what may properly be called the Riches or Treaſure of a Nation? Or what may be eſteemed the moſt Uſeful, after what is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Neceſſary, to ſupply the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Nature? Some being of Opinion that nothing doth deſerve that Name, or to be ſo eſteemed, but Gold and Silver; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no other Metal is ſo laſting and dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or ſo fit to receive the Royal Stamp,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93459:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>nor to be aſcertained in Value, and divided into ſeveral Denominations, nor ſo conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to pay Fleets and Armies; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hath a general eſteem in all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> as fit for ſuch uſes, and to be the Standard for the carrying on of Commerce, and to be Barter'd off for all other Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</p>
            <p>That Jewels, Lead, Tin or Iron, though durable, yet having not thoſe other quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, do not ſo well deſerve to be eſteemed Treaſure.</p>
            <p>That Silks, Woollen Goods, Wines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be eſteemed Riches between Man and Man, becauſe may be converted into Gold and Silver, yet do not deſerve to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Riches of the Nation, till by Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Foreign Countries are converted into Gold and Silver, and that brought hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe are ſubject to corruption, and in a ſhort courſe of Years will conſume to nothing, and then of no value.</p>
            <p>This being ſtated, if agreed, whoever will undertake to make out, that we have either by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade gained 1200000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum,</hi> as aſſerted, <hi>Page</hi> 15, 16. Or that the Nation did increaſe in Riches from <hi>Anno</hi> 1656 to <hi>Anno</hi> 1688, two Millions <hi>per Annum,</hi> muſt make out that ſo much was Imported in Bullion, over and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93459:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>above what was Exported: Which is ſo ſar from being generally believed, that many are of opinion, we have had our Treaſure Annually exhauſted ever ſince 1666, not only by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, but alſo by the great Exportation of our Coyn to the <hi>Northern</hi> Kingdoms to purchaſe Naval Stores, and Deals, Timber and Iron, uſed in the Rebuilding of <hi>London,</hi> and a greater number of Houſes ſince erected elſewhere, and to other places and Countries for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the many loſſes of Goods that were burnt by the Fire, or ſpoiled in removing, for the purchaſing of Foreign Commodities for the furniſhing of the new built Houſes, and to carry on the <hi>French</hi> Trade.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Anno</hi> 1656 to 1688 is 32 Years, which at 2 Millions <hi>per Annum</hi> is 64 Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. All that remember how plenty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was in this Nation <hi>Anno</hi> 1656, may find reaſon to conclude that we have not now in the Nation as much Gold and Silver as we had then. So that either the 64 Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions hath been ſpent ſince 1688, (which no Man can believe) or elſe was never gotten; which is moſt likely to be true: Becauſe, according to the beſt computation that can be made, it is concluded there hath not been Imported into <hi>Europe</hi> from <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica</hi> (from whence only any quantity of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93459:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Gold and Silver comes) ſince the Year 1656, much above 2 Millions <hi>per Annum,</hi> and it cannot well be imagined that we have got all to our ſhares: But if the Author had ſpent more thoughts, and ſtudy, to have found out where the 64 Millions he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be gotten, are now to be found, would have done the Nation a great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at this time.</p>
            <p>In juſtification of what hath been ſaid, that we loſe by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, as it hath of late Years been managed, theſe particulars are offered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it appears by the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe</hi> Books, that there was Enter'd in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies Name, Shipt out from <hi>Anno</hi> 1675 to <hi>Anno</hi> 1685, above 4 Millions, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 400000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum:</hi> And though it be difficult to make out exactly what was carried out, thoſe Years, by Interlopers or particular Perſons from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> to carry on Private Trade, yet it may be computed at 200000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the Goods brought from <hi>India</hi> and Exported, it doth not appear by ſuch Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations and Eſtimates that have been made, that 200000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> worth <hi>per Annum</hi> were ever Exported to <hi>Spain,</hi> or any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from whence we uſually Import Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93459:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="3">3. That from <hi>France, Holland, Turky, Italy,</hi> no returns uſually come in Bullion; what being brought in from <hi>Holland</hi> againſt any Sale, uſually going out again by the Courſe of Trade, ſeldom ſtayes long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not ſuppoſed the ballance of that Trade hath for many years ſtood long in our favour, nor till we apply our ſelves more to good Husbandry in the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Foreign Commodities, can well be expected ever will.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no rational account can be given of any Gold and Silver imported into this Kingdom to continue here, but what comes from <hi>Africa, Spain,</hi> and formerly <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſome ſmall Parcels ſometimes from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and that from all thoſe places we ſeldom have imported according to the beſt Calculations above 600000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> communibus annis</hi> for 30 years laſt paſt, and if ⅓ of that be allowed to be for <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Goods, it is the moſt that can well be reckoned; and that whatever we have Exported more in Bullion annually hath been loſt by that Trade; for what comes back in Goods to be conſumed here, makes us no amends for the Treaſure Exported, and Trades that cannot be ballanced with our own Products, ought to be rectified ſome other way, and not by ſending our Money to <hi>India</hi> to buy Goods for that purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93459:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Till theſe Objections be removed, we muſt be very credulous if we believe that the <hi>India</hi> Goods Exported bring us back as much Treaſure, as that Trade carries from us in Bullion, and if not brought in by the Goods ſold abroad, cannot poſſibly be brought in by the other half of thoſe Goods ſpent at home. But to ſalve that, it is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued in this Treatiſe, that nothing can be a clearer Gain than 600000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> by the Goods ſpent at home, becauſe ſo much would otherwayes have been Exported to purchaſe Foreign Silks and Linnens.</p>
            <p>But this Argument will appear to have no ground if our Courſe of Trade in Silks and Linnens from the <hi>European</hi> Nations be look't into, and how and for what uſes thoſe Silks and Linnens, and theſe from <hi>India</hi> are conſumed, that will make it plainly appear that theſe Goods from <hi>India</hi> do us no ſuch Service, and are ſo far from being a clear gains, upon any ſuch Account, that do not ſave us any thing material, but are pernicious in the higheſt degree.</p>
            <p>It is well known by all Traders, that the Silks imported from <hi>France</hi> were moſt Luſtrings and Alamodes which have been computed to amount to 400000 <hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> what other Silks came thence, were eſteemed for their being of ſome new faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93459:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>and were uſually high prized Rich Silks. The promoting of the Luſtring Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to Manufacture Luſtrings and Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modes here, and incouragement to our <hi>Weavers</hi> to make ſuch Rich Silks may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their coming from <hi>France,</hi> but which ſort of theſe Silks from <hi>India</hi> are ſpent in the room of Alamodes or Luſtrings or of any other Silks, that did uſually come from <hi>France,</hi> is unknown to thoſe skilled in that Trade. The Silks that uſually came from <hi>Holland</hi> were Velvets, Alamodes and Luſtrings; and from <hi>Italy,</hi> Velvets, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masks and Taffaties; though it be not doubted but the Silks from <hi>India</hi> do hinder the Conſumption of ſome Damasks, Taffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Sarſenets, yet being thoſe were all, or moſt, purchaſed by the Products of our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, we had better have them, then ſend our Money to the <hi>Indies</hi> to purchaſe theſe.</p>
            <p>Diaper, Dowlas, Canvas and Lockrams, which were four ſorts of Cloth that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the vaſt quantity of Linnens formerly imported from <hi>France,</hi> which as well as other Linnens taken from <hi>Hamburgh, Germany, &amp;c.</hi> were moſt uſed for Sheeting, Shifting, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and ſuch other uſes in Families as have not hitherto, nor is it likely will ever be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by theſe Linnens from <hi>India.</hi> The Muzlings and fine Linnens from <hi>India,</hi> it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93459:7"/>may be obſerv'd, are conſumed for long Cravats, Nightrails, Commodes and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow Curtains, (an Expence not known in <hi>England</hi> till within theſe 20 years) alſo for Aprons, and thus do hinder the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cambricks, and Lawnes, and the courſe Callicoes, of ſome courſe Cloaths. But if Cambricks and Lawnes, and moſt of ſuch courſe Linnens were all purchaſed with our Woollen Manufactures; then we ſhall find reaſon to conclude we did ill to introduce the Expence of theſe Linnens from <hi>India,</hi> which are ſo far from being a clear gain to <hi>England,</hi> as aſſerted Page the 16, that they are coſtly and miſchievous upon ſeveral Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>As it doth not appear upon theſe Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations that the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial by bringing in more Bullion than carries out or by hindring the Exportation of any of our Coin for Silks or Linnens; ſo it may be affirmed, that the Silks do us a further Miſchief by being ſpent directly in the room of our Stuffs made of Wooll, Hair, and mixt with Silk, and Worſted, and that no other ſilk made abroad, did ever ſerve for thoſe uſes, and therefore moſt dangerous.</p>
            <p>The Arguments derived from the great Gains made by that Trade, as by ſeveral
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93459:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Accompts in that Tract, ought to be lookt on, as blinds or baites for unthinking men; for if the accompts be not true, then the Arguments grounded thereon cannot be good. It is well known the Company doth not export the Goods they bring, but ſell them at a publick Sale, and that in the moſt flouriſhing times ſeldom got clear 50 <hi>per C.</hi> by ſuch Sales, the Merchants or Shop-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers who buy of them, get 10 to 20 <hi>per C.</hi> more, either by ſending abroad or retailing them here, adding to this what is paid for Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and Charges, yet all will fall much ſhort of this Computation, and that part which is thus gotten by Sales at home, is gotten by their being a Monopoly, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reckoned as gains to the Nation; and taking the Stock from <hi>Anno</hi> 1657. when firſt Incorporated to this day, there hath not been divided, (the Author owns Page 52,) not 20 <hi>per C.</hi> others think not 10 <hi>per C. per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> amongſt the Adventurers in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and the <hi>Crown,</hi> Capt. <hi>Dorrel,</hi> who went an Interloper, was thought to make an extraordinary Voyage, becauſe divided 50 <hi>per C.</hi> and few others ever made the like. So that without better Vouchers then are produced in that Tract, theſe Accompts ought not to paſs, neither ought we to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that what is pretended to be gotten
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93459:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade was ſo in Fact; no ſuch Gains having been divided amongſt the Adventurers, much leſs to the Nation, which may appear by their Books to be true, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Gains have been made by ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons; but if 300 <hi>per C.</hi> then muſt be hid as part of 64 Millions gotten by Trade ſince <hi>An.</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>And it cannot be denied, but that this Trade hath the Worſt Foundation of all the Trades we drive, becauſe carries from us Gold and Silver, which we cannot well ſpare, and brings us back Toyes, Handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft and manufactured goods, which we leaſt want, not only to the hindrance of the Conſumption of our Wooll, but the imployment of our people (from whence only Riches can have their original) and being the foundation is ſo bad, it will hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily be found impoſſible to make the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructure good. Meaſures taken of Trades, by the Gains made by the Traders, will alwayes prove Erroneous; from a due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of what ſorts of Commodities are Exported, and Imported, a true Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can only being made, whether the Trade to any Country be good or bad.</p>
            <p>As it hath been made out, that it is not probable that the Bullion Exported to <hi>India</hi> hath brought us back by the Goods tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93459:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>to Foreign Markets, and that the Goods ſold here do us any conſiderable ſervice, by hindering the Importation of Foreign Silks and Linnens; ſo it is plain, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Gains made by that Trade on the Goods ſold here is not Gains to the Nation, but gotten out of our own Peoples Pockets, by the Sales of ſuch Goods to the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Landed men, or others, who are the Conſumers, but not concerned in the Stock, by making them give great Rates for what they buy. The Nation by any ſuch Sales to our own People cannot be imburſed of the Treaſure ſent out, in Gold or Silver, or get more than they would by taking away an Eſtate from <hi>A.</hi> to give to <hi>B.</hi> But if this be a good way to bring Gains to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to carry on Trade by Joynt-Stocks, then certainly we have been very imprudent, not to ſet up more Monopolies for Trade; there being ſeveral Trades, as well as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, that might be named, of which if any Perſons could get a Monopoly, or the priviledge of the ſole Buying and Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, would as probably make four for one, or as much as can be made by theſe Goods from <hi>India.</hi> Thoſe that argue againſt this, have forgotten the Arguments amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which have been alwayes given by the Advocates for this Trade, for its being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93459:9"/>on in a Company with a Joynt-Stock, that when the Trade was Free and Open, before Incorporated <hi>Anno</hi> 1657, that all the Traders loſt by it; and it was the chief Reaſon given for obtaining that Charter, and what have ſince weighed very much for the ſupporting of this now in being.</p>
            <p>When Perſons that have a Trade Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated ſell their Goods at extravagant Rates to Foreign Countries, what may be gotten by ſelling them dear may in ſome caſes be advantagious to a Nation; but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gains made by any ſuch Perſons on Goods ſold to our own People to be ſpent at Home, will appear to be Gains made by working upon the Nation, not for the Nation; to the advantage of ſome by the prejudice of others.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that this Trade hath a good foundation, becauſe Materials are plenty, and Labour cheap in <hi>India;</hi> it being agreed that theſe Manufactured Goods are ſpent both Abroad and at Home, in the room of our own. This inſtead of being an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for recommending this Trade, will appear the moſt dangerous part of it: For unleſs our Wooll fall to nothing, and the Wages of thoſe that work it up to <hi>2d. per</hi> Day, and Raw Silk and Silk <hi>Weavers</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour proportionable, the <hi>India</hi> Goods will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93459:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>occaſion a ſtop to the Conſumption of them; becauſe thoſe from <hi>India</hi> muſt otherwiſe be Cheapeſt, and all People will go to the Cheapeſt Markets, which will affect the Rents of Land, and bring our Working People to Poverty, and force them either to fly to Foreign parts, or to be maintained by the Pariſhes: And therefore how the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are concerned in the Conteſt about this Trade, they may do well to conſider.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid in anſwer to this Propoſition, it may appear that as long as we manage the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade as we have of late Years, we ſhall loſe by it: That Gold and Silver is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or moſt uſeful Treaſure of a Nation: That we have not increaſed in Riches ſince <hi>Anno</hi> 1666: That the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Silks and Linnens at Home do us no ſervice, by hindering the expence of any Foreign Silks or Linnens: That the <hi>India</hi> Goods Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported do not bring us in near the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Gold and Silver Exported to carry on that Trade: That the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade hath a bad foundation: And that the great Gains made by Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, or Traders that carry on that Trade, is becauſe the Trade is confined
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93459:10"/>to ſome few Perſons, who are but as one Buyer and one Seller: And that nothing but Bullion Imported, can make amends for Bullion Exported. Which if not obſerved we may Trade away our Riches, but not get Riches by Trade.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Propoſition is, <hi>That to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the Wearing of</hi> Indian <hi>Silks,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>will be deſtructive to the Trade of</hi> England. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd under three Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>I.</hi> As relates to the Woollen Manufacture.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>II.</hi> As relates to the Silk and Linnen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>III.</hi> As to the effects ſuch a Prohibition will have.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> As relates to the Woollen Manufacture.</head>
               <p>By what is ſaid under this Head re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Woollen Manufacture it plainly appears, that the Author of this Treatiſe is of Opinion, that our Nobility, Gentry, and Landed Men, make too much of their Eſtates by ſelling their Wooll too dear; and that after many thoughts about it, had found out an effectual way to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy this evil, by endeavouring to perſwade them, that it is advantageous for us to ſend
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93459:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>our Money to the <hi>Indies</hi> to buy Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured Goods there, to be ſpent at Home, as well as Abroad, in the room of our Woollen Goods, which he endeavours to prove is their true Intereſt to do, as well as the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and that therefore it is their beſt way to ſell their Wooll very Cheap, and to get little by it, that it may be Exported: And for their Comfort tells them, that though they may thus make but little of their Wooll, yet that thoſe that drive the <hi>India</hi> Trade at the ſame time may make 400 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> of 100 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> Pa.</hi> 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33.</p>
               <p>That our Woollen Goods conſumed at Home do not inrich the Nation, and that a high Price on our Woollen Manufactures may hinder the Sale of them, is agreed; but that we muſt therefore ſend our Money to <hi>India</hi> to purchaſe the Manufactured Goods made in thoſe parts to be ſpent at Home, and Abroad, in the room of our own, in order to bring down the Price of them, by making Wooll and Labour cheap, are falſe Concluſions drawn from true Principles. If after we have uſed our beſt endeavours to keep up the Price of Wooll, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of our Woollen Goods, it ſhould be our misfortune to be diſappointed by the increaſe of ſuch Fabricks in other places, or diſuſe in the Expence of them, we ſhould
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93459:11"/>and ought to ſubmit with Patience; but it would be unanſwerable to be ſo zealous to have it done, as to give the firſt blow our ſelves by diſcouraging the Expence of them at Home.</p>
               <p>The Author of this Treatiſe might have done well to have told us to what price he would have Wooll fall, and in what places we can Conſume more Wollen Goods abroad, many Landed Men have for many Years paſt found Wooll already ſo Cheap, that cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great difficulty make their uſually Rents of Sheep ground now, and the generality of Merchants will own, that have not got by Trading in Woollen Goods for theſe 30 Years laſt paſt 6 <hi>per C. per Annum,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Adventures paid; and if it be conſidered how the Manufactures of Wooll are increaſed in <hi>Ireland, Holland, France, Germany, Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and what a Drugg our Manufactured Goods are become beyond the Sea, and that have been Export ed of late Years, rather out of Neceſſity to provide effects, then out of choice in hopes of Gaines; no Reaſon will appear for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Home, or incouraging the Expence of theſe Goods, if not in order totally to Ruin the Manufactury, unleſs we could be aſſured that the Falling of Wooll and Manufactures to a low Price, would firſt Ruin thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Manufactures, and then that ours
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93459:12"/>would certainly Advance in Price again; or that it could not be done by opening the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade, and making thoſe Goods Cheap, as well as by running down our own. And we ſhould alſo have been told how the Landed Men and Poor ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt whilſt the Experiment was making, and how in caſe this Project ſhould not take, we ſhould retrieve what we may Loſe by try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and how we ſhould regain the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of them at Home, after the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Goods have gotten Poſſeſſion by an unterrupted uſage: Unleſs theſe things be plainly made out, there will not appear any great Reaſon why we ſhould permit the <hi>India</hi> Goods to joſtle out the Expence of our own, and thereby occaſion the Fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Wooll, from 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> to 4 <hi>
                     <abbr>d.</abbr> per</hi> Pound; For if the Landed Men ſhould be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in their expectations, would then conclude that were Cullied out of their Mony by being perſwaded to part wich a Bird in Hand, in hopes to get another out of the Buſh from an unknown Country.</p>
               <p>What Woollens, Silks, Linnens, and other Goods of our own Make we ſpend at Home, are for the ſupply of our Neceſſities; and hitherto hath been thought very advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to ſave the Expence of ſuch or the like Goods from abroad, as well as to imploy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93459:12"/>our People; and that the expence of ſuch have always proved not only moſt Secure for our advantange, but the Cheapeſt: If we ſhould reject our own, and prefer the Conſumption of thoſe from <hi>India</hi> amongſt us, we may reaſonably expect that other Nations ſhould by our Example do the ſame, and ſo by our own endeavours deſtroy what we ought to be induſtrious to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</p>
               <p>It might as well have been argued that the beſt way for a Country Gentleman, that hath all Conveniences about his Houſe of his own, ſhould inſtead of uſing them for himſelf and Family, ſend his Mony to Market to buy, and then ſend his Products a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in hopes of making of Mony of them, though he do not know of any Market or Buyer for them; or that we ſhould not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our own Ships from <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> or from Port to Port on our Coaſt; but the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who Sail Cheaper, to force our own to ſeek imployment abroad, in hopes might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bring Mony to the Nation.</p>
               <p>But if it ſhould be underſtood that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what hath been ſaid it is our Intereſt to ſpend theſe <hi>Indian</hi> Goods at Home, that we may ſave our Woollen Goods to have the more for Exportation; if no ſtop muſt be put to ſpending them, either at Home
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93459:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>or abroad, ſeeing the 150000 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> worth, which were brought by the laſt three Ships will appear to be more, then it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed were brought here from the Year 1600, to <hi>Anno.</hi> 1670. though then a Trade was conſtantly driven to <hi>India:</hi> If ſuch great Gains be made on them, why may not the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Merchants be tempted to go on increaſing this Trade, till bring ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantities to ſupply all Markets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad as well as at Home. This is ſo far from being a groundleſs Suppoſition, if the Gains be ſo Great as repreſented, (or but 50 <hi>per C.</hi>) that according to the uſual Courſe of Trade, we may preſume that if this Trade be approved by authority may increaſe very faſt. For what Merchants will imploy their Stock, or their care to carry on the Trade in our Manufactures, when can have no hopes of more Gains then 6 <hi>per C.</hi> If by get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade and Dealings in thoſe Goods, may have ſuch great Profit as the Author hath Suggeſted: Therefore we ſhould have been told what we ſhould do with our Wooll, and our People too, if that Trade ſhould thus increaſe upon us, which is more probable then that the Expence of our Woollen Manufactures will increaſe, if the Conſumption of thoſe Goods from <hi>India</hi> be continued.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93459:13"/>
               <p>But leaſt theſe and ſuch like Arguments given in that Treatiſe to perſwade us that it is our intereſt to Conſume theſe Goods at Home, ſhould not be ſufficient: At laſt the old Bugbears the <hi>Dutch,</hi> are called upon to frighten us into it, who, as upon all occaſions when any conteſt hath happened about this Trade, are uſually Summoned for that purpoſe; and therefore it is ſaid Page the 33 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> that if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were forbid to bring <hi>India</hi> Goods into <hi>Europe,</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> would; and thereby hurt abroad the vent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloath: But this needs no anſwer here, it being not propoſed that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhall be Prohibited from bringing theſe Goods into <hi>Europe;</hi> but only the Conſumption of them in <hi>England;</hi> and the Conſumption of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloath were never underſtood to be much preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced by theſe Goods.</p>
               <p>This Head cannot be concluded better then with the Authors own Words, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>9th. As Bread is called the Staff of Life, ſo the Woollen Manufactures is truly the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Nouriſhment of our Body Politick;</hi> which being an undoubted Truth, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments in favour of <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Goods, that they ſhould be Conſumed, either at Home or abroad in the room of them, are the more to be admired, becauſe looks as contradictory as to affirm that the beſt way
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93459:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>for a Man to preſerve his Life, were to Cut his own Throat: And as much againſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the Carrying on of Trade, as that we ſhould Diſcourage the Expence of our own Corn at Home, on a Suppoſition that by ſending our Mony abroad, we may get Cheaper, and ſo force the Exportation of it; or that by Selling our own Cheap here, we may introduce the Exportation of it; or by having Woollen Goods from <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be ſpent here inſtead of our own, we may make great advantages by Exporting ours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> As to the Silk and Linnen Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures.</head>
               <p>Upon this Subject the Author labours to make out that Silk and Linnen are not the Genuine off-ſpring of this Kingdom, nor the Manufacturing of them Calculated for our Meridian: That though ſome of the Materials may be had from our own Soil, yet moſt from abroad: That our Wages are ſo high we can never expect any good from theſe Manufactures; and that therefore our People muſt be imployed upon our Wooll, that we may purchaſe Silks and Linnens from abroad, in Exchange of our Woollen Goods; and if we do not take that Courſe we ſhall Loſe our Trade to <hi>Silezia, Saxony,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93459:14"/>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Poland;</hi> and that it is the prudence of a State to ſee that induſtry and Stock be not diverted from things profitable, and turned upon Objects unprofitable.</p>
               <p>How Silks or Linnens perfectly Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factur'd in <hi>India,</hi> bought with our Mony ſhould be eſteemed more the Genuine off-ſpring of this Kingdom, or better Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for this Meridian, then our Silks and Linnens Manufactured at Home by our own People, is not apparent to all Mens underſtanding; eſpecially being the Linnens are Fabrickt with Materials of our own growth, and the Raw Silk we generally have, is purchaſed by the Product of our own Manufactures, and but of a ſmall value in proportion to the Labour beſtowed in making it up, (which muſt be owned to be all our own) and that we cannot ſpend our Goods in <hi>Turky</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> without taking their Silk in return: Upon all which the proper Queſtion is, whether we had beſt run the Adventure of Loſing or diſcouraging ſuch Manufactures at Home, and thoſe Trades abroad, rather then put any ſtop to the Conſumption of theſe beloved Goods from <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Author hath ſufficiently by ſuch Arguments diſcovered his Tranſports of zeal for the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade; ſo how
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93459:15"/>much prefers the Welfare of the <hi>Moguls</hi> Subjects, the advancing of his Lands, and the imploying of his People before thoſe of his own Country. Though many young Gentlemen have been prevailed with by Tradeſmen, or thoſe that ſerve them, to deſpiſe their own Products, and to ſpend in the room, what impoſed upon them by ſuch Traders; which hath too often ended in the deſtruction of their Eſtates; yet it may be ſaid to be a bold attempt to endeavour to perſwade the whole Body of the Nation, that it is their Intereſt to do ſo alſo; and to imploy none of their People on Silk and Linnen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all hands may be imployed on the Wollen Manufacture, that all ſuch Goods may thereby be Sold Cheap: But if Selling Cheap be ſo advantageous, and the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of our Landed Men, that the Lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods of ſo many People as live by the Silk and Linneen Manufactury, muſt be Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to effect it: Why hath he not given al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſome Arguments to have perſwaded our <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Merchants, or other Traders (who ſeldom think they get too much) to have given a good Example by Selling Cheap alſo? For without ſome ſuch, though the Landed Men ſhould ſink their Price of Wooll, and the Poor <hi>Weavers</hi> ſhould be taken off from the Silk and Linnen, that the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93459:15"/>Wooll might be Wrought up and Sold Cheap here to the Merchants, yet they may keep up the Price abroad, and Sell as dear as ever; and then this Project would occaſion a Loſs to the Landed Men, and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to theſe <hi>Weavers;</hi> only to give a good opportunity to thoſe that ſend ſuch Goods abroad, to Gain the more by them: And if the Author be of opinion that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Manufactured Goods from the <hi>India</hi> be ſo advantageous, and that Selling Cheap is the way to increaſe Conſumption; Why hath he not propoſed the opening of that Trade, that it may not be any longer a Monopoly, that thoſe Goods may alſo Fall in Price? For if there be 300 <hi>per C.</hi> gotten by them as he affirms, though ſhould Fall 200 <hi>per C.</hi> yet would afford more Gains to the <hi>East-India</hi> Merchants then the Wooll or Woollen Goods to the Landed Men, or Clothiers at the preſent Prizes; and be the occaſion of ſo great an increaſe of that Trade, that in a ſhort time we ſhould ſee no great need of taking of the <hi>Weavers</hi> from the Silk and Linnen Manufacture to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed on the Woollen: For the Goods from <hi>India</hi> would Supply the Markets in the room of them both abroad and at Home; that ſo there might not be any great need of many of them, eſpecially if none muſt be Spent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93459:16"/>at Home, as the Author would have it.</p>
               <p>But we are told <hi>Page</hi> 42. that ſome of the Materials for Linnens may be had from our own Soil, though too dear, and not enough: But the Author hath had the ill fortune to be miſinformed in that alſo; for the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> alone, will afford as much Flax (if incouragement were given for the Manufacturing of Linnen) as to make ſufficient to furniſh all <hi>England;</hi> and the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> as well as others, would be found capable to ſupply any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; and that there are many poor People in <hi>Durham</hi> that work for 3 <hi>
                     <abbr>d.</abbr> per</hi> Day; and that they make a Thread ſo fine as to be worth 12 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> Pound; and that there is Linnen of 7 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> per</hi> Ell made at <hi>Malton</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> and that we could make ſorts fit for Tabling, Sheeting and Shifting, upon which the great expence of Linnen depends, very good and ſufficient for ſuch uſes, to furniſh the Nation: If cannot well be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded ſo Cheap as to conteſt with what comes from Foreign Parts, yet ſhould not be diſcouraged upon a ſuppoſition, that it is not the genuine off-ſpring of this Kingdom; for many Manufactures in this and ſeveral Countries, from a ſmall beginning, have come to great Perfection, and therefore ought to have all incouragement given to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93459:16"/>it. That it is not come to more Perfection may happily, upon Examination, be found our own fault.</p>
               <p>If the original, or chief cauſe or means of Riches muſt be from the Labour of our People, how do ſuch Arguments, as are uſed in this Tract, conſiſt with that Maxim? Our Woollen Manufactures muſt be reduced to near one half by not ſpending them at Home, Silk and Linnen Manufactures not convenient, and if Paper and Shooes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had ſtood in the way of <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Goods, it is probable that by the ſame way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thoſe would have been cryed down alſo: And being about 40000 Fans came in the laſt Ships from <hi>India,</hi> with ſome Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicrafts Wares, as uſual in all Ships, if they ſhould be permitted to increaſe, with the Silks and Linnens from thoſe parts, being purchaſed with Bullion, how ſhall the State imploy the People upon Profitable Objects, or prevent Poverty from growing upon us, unleſs could find out Mines of Gold and Silver: And therefore we ſhould have been told, how our Induſtry and Stock could have been better imployed then in ſuch Manufactures, before ſuch advice ſhould be given for the diſcouragement of Woollen, Silks and Linnen.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93459:17"/>
               <p>But upon the concluſion of this matter, the Author ſeems to be of Opinion that Silk and Linnen may do well in proceſs of time, when <hi>England</hi> ſhall come to be more Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, and when a long Peace hath increaſed our Stock and Wealth; but the Author doth not tell us how the People we have ſhall live in the mean time, nor of any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability how our Stock or Wealth ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, nor how we ſhall then ſet up again, promote or incourage ſuch Manufactures, if we ſhould now permit them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, being our being in War is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Sale of ſome of thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; neither doth he tell us by what we ſhall get Money to carry on this <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade in the mean time: For ſome are of Opinion, that our Trade to <hi>India</hi> hath been carried on by Money ariſing from the Labour of our People imployed in other Trades, and not by the Gains or Returns we make by it; neither doth he tell us how we ſhall get Money to purchaſe the Linnen and Silk he would have us take from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, nor what incouragement will be left for the increaſing of People if theſe Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 28. and 34. having well argued how it is our Intereſt to imploy the People we now have, and that we want more; it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93459:17"/>looks like a Contradiction to argue, that we ſhould not imploy any in fabricking Silk or Linnen, nor on Woollen Goods to be ſpent at Home. All to the Plow and Cart may be too many; and ſuch as have been bred in Inland Countries have not a Genious, Spirit, or Inclination to the Fiſhing Trades.</p>
               <p>If the Author of this Tract had gone as often to <hi>Spittle-Fields</hi> or <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as it may be preſumed he hath to the <hi>India-Houſe,</hi> and had informed himſelf what vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both Sexes, and of all Sizes, are imployed in that Manufactury, and had their ſole dependance thereon, would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably have received ſuch impreſſions as to have induced him to have forborn giving the Opinions he hath about that Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and have been convinced, that our <hi>Engliſh Weavers,</hi> even in that Manufacture, have ſhewed themſelves able to conteſt with the <hi>French, Dutch</hi> and <hi>Italian,</hi> both as to Price and Goodneſs, notwithſtanding the great Misfortune we lye under, of having ſo many of our Gentry fond of no Silks but what come from Abroad. That this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture hath increaſed very much in this laſt Age, notwithſtanding theſe difficulties, is an undeniable Proof againſt what is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, that this Manufactury cannot thrive in <hi>England.</hi> Men being ſo apt to mind their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93459:18"/>particular Intereſt in matters of Trade, that it is to believe a great Contradiction, that it ſhould ſo much increaſe if it could have been out-done by the <hi>French, Dutch</hi> or <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Silks, ſo as to have prevented the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers or Maſter <hi>Weavers</hi> from making Profit by them; and how they have improved, to make them as good (if not better) than any made beyond Sea, may be evident to any perſon that will make an inquiry, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine or compare them, with what come from Abroad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> As to the Effect ſuch a Prohibition would have upon the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade in General.</head>
               <p>Upon this Head it is argued, that it will endanger the loſs of half that Trade. If he mean that part of the Trade which is carried on by the Importation of Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured Goods, Handicraft Wares, China, Lacquer'd Ware and Toyes; and would have it underſtood, that a ſtop to the going out of our Money to purchaſe theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, would occaſion any Loſs to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> would have done well, Firſt, to have made out that ever we gained by thoſe Commodities; otherwayes there be many
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93459:18"/>that would not be much troubled to have that part of the Trade loſt; it being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that the Salt-Petre, Druggs, Spices, and Courſe Callicoes, are all the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities we ever had from thence, that were neceſſary for us; and there can be no great danger the <hi>Mogul</hi> will deny us thoſe, tho' we ſhould leave him theſe for his own uſe; becauſe till about the Year 1670, we did not uſually take any others from him: And it may be difficult to find out any way to make that Trade Profitable, but by confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelves to thoſe Commodities, that we may ſend out little Money, and by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from Port to Port, and making Gains there in Trafficking with the <hi>Indians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Arguments againſt any ſuch Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, becauſe no ſuch Law would be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, may be made againſt any new Law, and ſuppoſeth a ſtrange Weakneſs in our Legiſlative Power; and that being one half of the Goods from <hi>India</hi> are ſpent at Home, there will be no incouragement for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants to ingage in this Trade to <hi>India.</hi> If muſt ſingly depend on the Markets Abroad, is contrary to what hath been practiced; for there was an <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ingaged in theſe Manufactured Goods, and againſt his own Opinion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to our own Goods; having a little
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93459:19"/>before argued that our Woollen Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures ſhould all be ſent Abroad; which may be as great a diſcouragement to <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Clothiers</hi> or <hi>Weavers,</hi> to ingage in thoſe, as for the <hi>India</hi> Merchants in theſe: And if it be agreed (as it is) that either our Woollen Goods, or thoſe Silks, muſt travel, Why ſhould we not rather put that difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon theſe Goods, than upon our own? But at laſt would not have the preſent time good for ſuch an Alteration, nor have it done raſhly, nor without contemplating the Univerſal Trade of the Nation, whereas this Matter hath been already under Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration Fifteen Years, and without much time in Contemplation, we might be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that our Coyn growes ſcarce, and that this Trade hath for ſeveral Years carried out near as much Bullion as we have Imported from all parts of the World.</p>
               <p>But leaſt all this ſhould not prevail to have this Trade continued, the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as uſual, are again muſtered up; though upon a due Conſideration of their Trade to <hi>India,</hi> and how it is carried on, no well grounded Argument can be brought for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this branch of that Trade from any thing relating to that Nation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> having had the ſole poſſeſſion of the Iſland of <hi>Ceylon,</hi> the chief Iſlands in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93459:19"/>
                  <hi>India</hi> for Cloves, Cinnamon and Nutmegs, for about Forty Years, and got the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Bantam,</hi> where Pepper is Plenty, and of other places where Spices are to be had: By that Commodity, and by Trading with their Ships, Spices and Goods, in thoſe parts, and bringing Home what thus got, for the <hi>European</hi> Markets, no doubt have made it an Advantageous Trade to them; but they never ſent out any conſiderable parcel of Gold or Silver for <hi>India,</hi> till after we had ingaged in bringing Home theſe Silks and Fine Linnens; then the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company in <hi>Holland,</hi> to make Gains for themſelves, though with the danger of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Manufactures of their own Country, by our Example, ingaged alſo in theſe; but ſtill carry on the Trade in them with a great advantage to us; for though have brought many of theſe Goods, yet never ſent out one ſeventh part ſo much Bullion as we, and have alwayes uſed their utmoſt endeavours to diſcourage the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of theſe Goods in their own Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and yet they are complain'd off there, as much as here, and ſtops and reſtraints are often put upon the bringing of them from <hi>India:</hi> But if there muſt not be a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Stop or Prohibition till both theſe <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Companies Conſent to it, we may
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93459:20"/>expect it, but in vain, till Temptations ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from Private Intereſt (however oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Publick) be extirpated. The <hi>Dutch Eaſt-India</hi> Company will alwayes argue for the Continuance of this Trade, becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> bring them; and the <hi>Engliſh Eaſt-India</hi> Company for bringing of them, becauſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> do: But the <hi>Dutch</hi> having them upon much better terms than we, may probably hold out longeſt. But the Trade being carried on there by a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly, as well as here, and great Men concerned, no Judgment can be made by the Gains that Trade affords to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, whether the Trade be good or bad. As for Spices, Druggs and Saltpetre, the way to have more of them, is to confine the Trade to ſuch Commodities; theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not being made, by the <hi>Indians,</hi> till the Factors beſpeak them. Till ſome ſuch Limitation be made, theſe affording moſt Profit will be preferred, and we were not debar'd the having thoſe when we did not ingage in this Trade of Manufactured Goods, and little Reaſon to fear we ſhall be now.</p>
               <p>This Head is concluded with an Accompt of Pepper, which with the other Accompts in this Tract, do not agree with other Mens Opinions, about the Gains made by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93459:20"/>this Trade; for if the General Adventurers in the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Stock in <hi>Holland,</hi> compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the Original of that Stock to this Day, have not made 5 <hi>per Cent.</hi> by their Money put in, as all Perſons do agree that have any Knowledge thereof, if this vaſt Gains be made by this Trade, who runs away with it? The like Queſtion may be properly put, as to this Trade here; If 100 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> imployed in this Trade have produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced uſually 400 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr>,</hi> as ſo often aſſerted in this Treatiſe, it muſt be thought ſtrange, that the Adventurers that underwrit this Stock <hi>Anno</hi> 1657, if had continued their Shares to this Day would not have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much above 10 <hi>per Cent. per Annum,</hi> notwithſtanding the great Advantages made for ſeveral Years, by confining their Stock (for making large Dividends) to 375000 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> and Trading with other Peoples Money, taken up at 4 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Unleſs this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery be explained, both as to <hi>Holland</hi> and here, there will remain a Doubt, That if there be any ſuch Gains, that it is ſwallow'd up by ſome particular Perſons, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Publick Good, to carry on a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt; and that both Nations will in time find, that they have but dreamt of making ſuch Vaſt Gains by this Trade, in theſe Goods; and that the Gains made in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93459:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>both Countries by Stock-Jobbing, and other indirect or private wayes, by ſuch as have got into the Management, is the true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why there hath been ſo much ſtrugling about this Trade more than about others, that upon a true Calculation would be found more Beneficial.</p>
               <p>The Author of this Tract having owned <hi>Page</hi> 12. as to the Trade to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> in General that it is naught, and that if all <hi>Europe</hi> would agree to have no further Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to thoſe Parts, would certainly ſave a great Expence of Treaſure, becauſe <hi>Europe</hi> drawes nothing from thence of ſolid uſe, only periſhable Commodities, and Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials to ſupply Luxury, in return of Gold and Silver, which is there buried and never returns; but would have the Burthen to fall upon the Collective Body of <hi>Europe.</hi> It is concluded, that nothing could be more fatal than this Aſſertion, to all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this Diſcourſe, to render this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a manner, undone, if the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Indian</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> Silk be Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited; upon which (it is ſaid) the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of above half of that Trade depends, and half our Foreign Buſineſs. <hi>Page</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>It is well known that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> drive the greateſt Trades of all <hi>European</hi> Nations, and that doth depend much upon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93459:21"/>the Conſumption of their own Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures: If theſe <hi>Indian</hi> Silks be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, as is owned <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>31st.</hi> in the room of our Stuffs, Anthorines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Linnens, as well as the Silks (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of in <hi>Holland</hi>) in the room of the Silks and Linnens Manufactured there, and we ſpend half at home of what is brought from thence, and all purchaſed with our Gold and Silver; why may not <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> be taken in amongſt the Collective Body of <hi>Europe,</hi> upon whom this Loſs doth Fall, and be found to bear the greateſt Share by the Loſs that theſe Manufactured Goods occaſions, whatever Gains do or might make by the other Branches of that Trade? For other Nations that Conſume ſuch Goods, becauſe have none of their own Fabrick, cannot be at any Loſs in ſo doing; do but Lay out their Mony in theſe Goods, inſtead of Laying it out in the Woollens made by us, or Linnens made by the <hi>Dutch:</hi> All Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions not being ſo extravagant, as to ſpend ſo much the more becauſe theſe Goods are brought them: Therefore as may truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Author, that this Trade is Naught for <hi>Europe</hi> in general, ſo very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for this Nation, which indeed ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers moſt by it, becauſe we altered the Management of it ſince the Year 1670. Of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93459:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>which ſome hints are given before, and might be made apparent; but omitted for this time, leaſt it ſhould be thought ſtrange that the Author ſhould not be in the Right, neither when Argues againſt this Trade, nor for it.</p>
               <p>But to conclude with ſome Obſervations upon what mentions of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> Page the <hi>6th.</hi> that had left behind him an Evidence how much had made Matters of Trade, his care and Study; and that thereby had laid the only Foundation of a Solid and laſting greatneſs: If he had alſo taken Notice of the Edicts, Tariffs and Orders made ſince, and of the Politicks practiſed in <hi>France</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to Trade, particularly of the Edict made the <hi>26th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1686. for Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Deſtoying <hi>China</hi> Silks, Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other Goods from <hi>India,</hi> would have found that they have proceeded quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to what propoſed in this Treatiſe, and that have found their end by it; For by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Conſumption of their own Manufactures both at Home and abroad, and their Fiſhing Trades have increaſed their Riches, Seamen and Navigation, to ſuch a degree in 40 Years time, as hath enabled them to maintain a long War with moſt of the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> without much help from the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade; and that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93459:22"/>therefore we may conclude a Nation may Thrive by Trade, without that to the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> and that they have been as much in the Right in the managing of their Trade, as we have been in the Wrong in the Management of ours.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>By what hath been ſaid, it may appear that the Manufactured Goods from <hi>India,</hi> Spent and Conſumed in <hi>England,</hi> cannot by any way be Inſtrumental to prevent the going out of our Coin, nor to the bringing in of Gold and Silver to make amends for what Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to Carry on that Trade: And that unleſs it can be made out by very good Proof or Demonſtration that by the return of <hi>India</hi> Goods we Tranſport to Foreign Countries, we bring Home in Gold and Silver more then we Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, for the Carrying on of that Trade, that we ought to conclude that our Treaſure hath been Exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Trade; and that it hath been miſchievous to us in the higheſt degree, by hindring our Woollen Manufactures as well as the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe for Silk and Linnen: All which is ſubmitted to better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               </q>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93459:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Amongſt the ſcattered Notions laid down in that Treatiſe referring to Trade, the Author Obſerves, <hi>Page</hi> 11.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That in our great Aſſemblies it hath never been ſufficiently thought a matter of State, but manag'd rather as a conveniency, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental Ornament, then the chief ſtrength and ſupport of the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>That as it hath never been greatly the care of our Ministers of State; ſo it hath not been enough the Study of Nobility and Gentry, who (give me leave to ſay) for want of a right Knowledge in the general Notions of it, have been frequently impoſed upon by particular Merchants, and other intereſted Perſons to Enact Lwsa, ſo much to the prejudice of Trade in General.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> That Trade is in its Nature free, finds its own Channel, and beſt directs its own Courſe; and all Laws to give it Rules and directions, and to Limit and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribe it, may ſerve the particular ends of private Men, but are ſeldom advantageous to the Publick.</p>
                  <p>That Governments in Relation to it, are to take a Providential care of the whole; but generally to let Second Cauſes work their own way; and Conſidering all the Links and Chains by which they hang together, peradventure it
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93459:23"/>may be affirmed that in the main all Trafficks whatſoever, are Beneficial to a Country.</p>
                  <p>That few Laws in a State are an indication of Wiſdom in a People; but it may be truly ſaid that few Laws Relating to Trade are the Mark of a Nation that Thrives by Traffick.</p>
               </q>
               <p>What is ſaid, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> cannot eaſily be reconciled with what is ſaid, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> For if Trade muſt be Free without being Limited or reſtrained by any Laws, what need is there, that our Nobility and Gentry, who make our great Aſſembly, ſhould apply themſelves to Study a right Knowledge of it? For according to this Opinion, no Laws Relating to Trade ſhould be Enacted, becauſe are ſeldom Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to the Publick; And that all Trade whatſoever is Beneficial; and yet the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is of Opinion, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> that no Wiſdom can give the Publick effectual help till we can mend the Condition and Poſture of Trade.</p>
               <p>But taking it for Granted that what is ſaid, <hi>Page</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> is but a Complement to our Nobility and Gentry, and to ſave their time, that may not ſpend it about what is unneceſſary: and that what is ſaid, <hi>Page</hi> 25. That Trade ought to be Free, is the Authors Opinion, becauſe beſt agrees with the whole deſign of the Book: It being ſo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93459:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Point, that all Laws already made and all Propoſals for any Future Regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons depend upon the deciſion thereof; ſhould not be reſolved without a due Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of ſuch Arguments and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations as may be proper to lay Open the State of the Caſe: To which it is hoped, being the ingenious Author tells us, hath applyed his Thoughts and Study to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Trade, he will afford his aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>If Trade muſt be left to take its own Courſe, find out its own Channel, and not be under any Reſtrictions or Limitations by Laws, on a Suppoſition that all Trades Naturally afford Profit and Advantage to a Nation; then the Act of Navigation and all other Laws Relating to Trade ſhould be repealed, and all Conſiderations for making any more for Future laid aſide.</p>
               <p>Though the Author ſeems to incline to this Opinion, and it be known that many others agree with him in it, yet upon Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination it may appear a vulgar and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Error.</p>
               <p>For the firſt Foundation that ſhould be laid for the preſerving or increaſing of Trade, is to have a Stock, which Stock ſhould be in Mony; then to uſe all endeavours to preſerve and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it by Frugality in the Conſumption of Foreign Commodities and Labour and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93459:24"/>induſtry, for the increaſing and promoting the Conſumption of our own.</p>
               <p>So long as the Nation keeps to Frugality and induſtry Laws may not be abſolutely Neceſſary to Limit the Conſumption of any Foreign Commodities, nor to increaſe or promote our own Manufactures: But if there be an appearance, that a Nation is running into a luxurious Prodigal Expence of Foreign Comodities, and to a neglect in Manufacturing and promoting their own, and to idleneſs, and ſpending of time in what is not profitable for the Nation, the uſual Conſequences of Luxury, (which we fear is our Caſe at preſent) then Laws will be neceſſary to put a ſtop to it, that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Nation may not be Conſumed thereby: For by the Courſe of Trade no ſtop can happen to any ſuch Conſumptions nor Idleneſs, till want of Money occaſion it. To omit making ſuch Laws upon any ſuch occaſion, would be to permit, that which is of the greateſt importance to run the laſt extremity, rather then agree that it ſhould be prevented by prudential Laws made by the State, or any endeavours uſed for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>As it hath been Suggeſted that Gold and Silver is the only, or at leaſt moſt uſeful and beſt deſerving to be called the Treaſure of a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93459:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>Nation, and ſo neceſſary for the Carrying on of Commerce, that when ever plenty of that fails, we may expect that Trade will in a great meaſure fail alſo; ſo it may be affirmed that Bartering of Commodities can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſupply the want thereof, becauſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make any quick Progreſs; neither can it be ſupplied by Credit, becauſe Credit muſt have its Original and exiſtence from an expectation or aſſurance of Money.</p>
               <p>All Traders have Reaſon to make it their buſineſs to get Money by their Trades, by ſending out and bringing Home ſuch Commodities as are moſt vendible, and yield them moſt Profit: But whether ſend out Goods or Bullion, or whether what bring back be neceſſary for the ſupply of our Neceſſities, or uſeful for a further Manufacture, or be ſpent in Prodigality, Luxury, or Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or to the hindrance of our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture (ſo long as they get by it) they do not generally take it to be their Province to mind: But for the good of the whole, it may be preſumed the State ought to mind it ſo far, as may be convenient to prevent the Exportation of our Treaſure; if not, the Stock of Gold and Silver, which is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to Carry on Trade, as well as for our Defence, will be Conſumed; by which the Traders themſelves as well as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93459:25"/>the generality will in time be involved in Miſery.</p>
               <p>Though Riches cannot be gotten, but from Foreigners, by having our Ships im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by them, or dealings with them, or by our Exporting and ſelling to them, to a greater value, than we purchaſe and take from them, that the overplus may be brought home in Bullion; yet no Trades carried on by the Exportation of own Products, and Manufactures, or thoſe from our Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though what brought back in return, be all periſhable Commodities, can diminiſh our Riches, for all ſuch Goods of ours (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome Objection be made as to Tin and Lead) would have periſht by time, if had been kept here; but a great diſtinction ought to be made, between Trades carried on by the Exportation of our Products, and Trades carried on by the Exportation of our Bullion, to purchaſe periſhable Commodities, becauſe in ſuch caſewe Exchange what is durable, and moſt uſeful, for what cannot long do us any Service.</p>
               <p>Suppoſing Three Millions of Coyn be at preſent the Stock of the Nation Circulating for the carrying on of Trade, as long as it is laid out in our own Products, and Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures, and ſuch are Exported, though whatever be brought in return of them pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93459:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>in a ſhort time, yet our Stock will be good, and ſo long Trade will be carried on: But if inſtead of carrying on Trade by the Exportation of our Goods, we ſhould ſend out, a Million in Coyn or Bullion to the <hi>India,</hi> to purchaſe Silks, another Million to <hi>France</hi> to purchaſe Wines and Brandies, and another Million to purchaſe Fruit, or Toyes, and all be ſpent at home, we may ſoon find the Treaſure of the Nation conſumed, our ſtock of Gold and Silver which we had for the carrying on of Trade, in the hands of Foreigners, and the Goods we had in return, in the Draynes, or on the Dunghil.</p>
               <p>If this be obvious repreſented thus in groſs, then leſſer parcels of Money ſent out to purchaſe ſuch Goods (by the Rule of Proportion) muſt have the ſame Effect in ſome Degree; by all which it may appear that what is aſſerted, Page the 25, <hi>That all Traffick is beneficial to a Country,</hi> cannot be true, as to ſome Trades; that ſome Traders for their private Gains may be tempted to carry on, who may get by Trade, and yet the Nation may loſe at the ſame time by ſuch Trades.</p>
               <p>And therefore if no Laws muſt be made to promote the Making or Conſumption of our own Goods, nor to hinder the Importation
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93459:26"/>or Conſumption of any from abroad, it muſt inevitably follow, that when ever a Nation falls into Luxury, and the People to Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or to ſpend their Time in Imployments unprofitable to a Nation, ſuch a Nation muſt be reduced to beggery by Trade, without any hopes or proſpect that it can be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, till their Treaſure be Exhauſted, and no Money left to carry on ſuch Trades, unleſs the Government interfere to hinder the Conſumption of ſuch Commodities, as upon an exact inquiry may be found, do carry out our Coyn, either by Prohibitions, or rather by Example, or high Impoſitions laid upon the Vending and Conſuming of them at home; which happily may be found moſt in offenſive, as to Foreign States, and not difficult to be contrived, and made effectual, and not prove any great hindrance to Trade, or to many Trading Men, if will have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Poſterities, and Common Good, as well as to their preſent Gain. For as the Conſumption of ſome Commodities may be hinder'd thereby ſo will make room for their Trading in others; and prove but a taking them off from Vending Goods unprofitable to the Nation, to Trade in Goods that may be more convenient.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93459:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is agreed that the beſt way to incourage Trade, and make it advantageous to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and uſeful to afford a livelihood to the vaſt Number of People that have their Sole dependance thereon, is in general to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all the liberty imaginable; but as moſt general Rules may be liable to ſome excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo this eſpecially to theſe two: Firſt, that no Trade ought to be incouraged that is carried on by the Exportation of our Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, unleſs to purchaſe what we abſolutely want for our Defence, or Support of Life, and we cannot poſſibly have on better Tearms, or where we may have an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted indiſputable aſſurance that the Goods purchaſed with it will bring in more Bullion, in Bullion, by the Sales of ſuch Goods abroad, than was carried out. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that no Wooll be carried out raw and unwrought. Other Laws may be found neceſſary to prevent abuſes in the Manufactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Goods, keeping the People to Work, and for the incouraging and increaſing of Trade, which ſhould be applied as Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Exigencies may require, but none appear neceſſary (upon theſe ſudden thoughts) contrary to the Freedom inſiſted on, but what may be Comprehended under theſe two Exceptions here mentioned.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93459:27"/>
               <p>Where it appears plain that a Trade is carried on by the Exportation of our Coin and Exhauſting of our Treaſure, no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can be given that it muſt not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, becauſe may hinder the Gains or Imployments of ſome Perſons, that can have much more weight in that particular, than what might have been offer'd againſt the wicked Trade of Clipping, for though the Livelihoods many got by that Trade, were juſtly more obnoxious to the Law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe was a ſecret Robbery, and upon many accounts indanger'd the Peace and Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and welfare of the Nation; yet being what was ſo wickedly got, doth not appear to be ſent out (unleſs to be exchanged from Silver to Gold,) the Nation did not loſe ſo much Treaſure by it, as hath and will, by Trades carried on by the Exportation of our Coyn, as long as permitted.</p>
               <p>Whether Trade left at full Liberty to be carried on, by the Exportation of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts and Manufactures may produce Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, will much depend upon good Sales to our Commodities abroad, and good Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry in the Conſumption of Foreign Commodities at home, but the having of many ſorts of Manufactures of our own is not onely the beſt way to have Variety to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93459:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſend abroad, but to prevent our being in want of ſuch Commodities, that there may be no Temptation for their being Imported; but no Trade more likely to bring us in a good proportion of Bullion, then out Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Trades; not only becauſe in is procur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Labour, without any great Coſt by Foreign Materials, but being a Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity neceſſary abroad for the ſupport of Life, ſeldom fails of Markets, and ready Money, which is often brought home in <hi>Speaie</hi> from many places, and is alſo a Commodity not likely ever to go out of Requeſt; for which, and becauſe thoſe Trades are alſo a Nurſery for Seamen, it may be found our true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to favour thoſe Trades with the beſt Protection, and Incouragement. And thus the Authors Maxime, Page the 38. <hi>That it is the Prudence of a State to ſee that Induſtry and Stock be not diverted from things profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the whole, and where a Nation is a certain known gainer, to be turn'd upon Objects unprofitable, or new Inventions, in which it cannot be determined in many years whether we get or loſe, or how the Ballance ſtands;</hi> may be put in practice with all the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty imaginable, as well as by the Fiſhing Trades as by the Woollen Silk and Linnen Manufacture, and happily upon Examination
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:93459:28"/>will be found more Politick, then as the Author would have it applied, in favour of the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade.</p>
               <p>But it being ſuppoſed that the <hi>Dutch</hi> will be here again brought upon the Stage, and the Liberty they give in matters of Trade, and for the Exportation of Money, object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt what is here argued; to make one anſwer for all, which is ſuppoſed may be ſatisfactory, not only againſt all Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that can be derived from the Practices of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> for an unlimited Freedom in Trade, but as to what hath been argued or may relate to the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trade alſo; Let it be agreed that we ſhall live in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as Parſimonious as they do in <hi>Holland,</hi> and be as Induſtrious in our Fiſhing, and ſome other Trades (that might be named) as they are, and that we ſhall not ſend out more Bullion to the <hi>India</hi> for the carrying on of that Trade, then they do, or that we ſhall have great Impoſitions upon ſuch Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Commodities as may be found to be the occaſion of the Exhauſting of our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or pernicious to our own Manufactures, to ſecure us from ſuch inconveniences as are feared from ſuch Liberty; then all diſputes ſhall ceaſe, as to all Prohibitions relating to Trade: But if we muſt not be lead, nor take
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93459:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>Example from them in Parſimony, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, we ought not to be lead by them in making of Laws relating to the Exportation of our Coin, or Prohibitions of Goods; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whether ſuch Laws be good and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or not, depends wholly upon the Genius and Inclination of the People. If Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimonious and Induſtrious, then no need of ſuch Laws; but if Luxurious and Idle, muſt be Ruin'd without them; and this is well known to thoſe States where ſuch Liberty is granted which makes them very obſervant of their old Cuſtoms and Faſhions, and very diligent and careful to keep their People to Work, as may be inſtanced in <hi>Holland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though it may be as difficult to give a true account of the Turnings, Windings, Circulations, Steps, Degrees and Progreſs of Trade, and Drawing and Redrawing by Exchange, as to give a certain account of all the Veins, Arteries, Fibres, Circulation of the Bloud, Cauſes of Diſeaſes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in a Body Natural, yet there are ſome plain Caſes relating to both, which may be agreed without penetrating into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Miſteries of either.</p>
               <p>That we ſhould ſend out to <hi>India</hi> about 600000 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum</hi> in Bullion, though it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93459:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath been never yet made out that thoſe Goods bring us back again in Bullion, the value of 200000 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> and much of it, to be there laid out, to purchaſe Manufactured Goods to be ſpent in the room of our own, or that we ſhould ſend out Bullion to any place to buy Goods to be ſpent in Luxury, or in the room of ſuch as we can make by our own people, or that we ſhould Export our Wooll Raw, to be Manufactured abroad, when the Advantage by Manufacturing it at home would be near ſeven parts in Ten ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, however may agree with ſome Mens Intereſt, cannot well be for the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Nation, nor the beſt way to gain or retain Riches; for no Gains made by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Men, can make a recompence for the loſs the Nation will receive by having their Stock of Money Conſumed, and the Poor beaten out of their Imployment.</p>
               <p>Sufficient Care being taken by Prohibiting or Diſcouraging the Conſumption of ſuch Goods as occaſion the carrying out of our Coyn, or Bullion, and for encouraging the working of our Wooll at home, no Liberty ſhould be thought too much to be given, for the carrying on of Trades by a permu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Commodities, not only by a free Exportation and Importation, but without
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93459:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>being Subject to the Payment of great Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties becauſe will be found the beſt way to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Trade, and make it beneficial, for though it may be difficult to give a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar account how, or what gains, may ariſe to a Nation, or particular Men, by every diſtinct Trade, yet ſo long as carried on by the Exportation of our Products, or what other Goods we may have, there can be no danger of loſing, for the particular Traders will take care not to carry on Trades by which they do not get, and ſuch Gains made by the Collective body of Traders, may properly be ſaid to be the Gains of the Nation, <hi>and Trade thus carried on may be left to take its own Courſe, and find its own Channel, and to work by Second Cauſes its own Way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Author having Aſſerted, Page 11, <hi>That it will be found at laſt, when all things come to be rightly underſtood, that no Plenty at Home, Victory Abroad, Affection of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Conduct or Wiſdom in other things, can give the Publick effectual help, till we mend the Condition or Poſture of Trade.</hi> It is hoped that as he hath obliged the Publick, with his Excellent Book of <hi>Wayes and Means,</hi> ſo if do not agree with ſuch Notions as theſe, that he will communicate his Thoughts
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93459:30"/>how the Condition and Poſture of Trade can be mended, by purſuing any others, and how or which way a Nation can get by Trade; as long as by a Prodigal Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Foreign Commodities and neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſcouraging of our own, we take in more than we ſend out, and then Export our Gold and Silver to pay the Ballance, which will be found to be our Caſe, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſpecious pretences may be made by thoſe that make Profit by ſending out our Gold and Silver to hide the true reaſon from the Nobility and Gentry, whoſe Application of Thoughts upon theſe Subjects, would no doubt be of great Uſe, not only to the Publick, but, to their particular Intereſts.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>LAtely Publiſhed a Book Intituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe of Trade and Coyn;</hi> in which moſt of the Notions mentioned in this Tract referring to Trade are inlarged. Sold by <hi>B. Alymer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93459:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
